Based on and inspired by the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi, this series
シュリ・マタジ・ニルマラ・デヴィの教えに基づいて インスピレーションを得たこのシリーズ
aims to explore the evolutionary relationship between two interconnected domains
2つの相互に関連した領域間の進化的関係を 探求することを目的としています
expressing human awareness at the gross and subtle levels.
人間の意識を全体のレベルと精妙なレベルで表現します
It endeavors to elucidate this complex interplay between the current scientific understanding
これは、現在の科学的理解と
of human neuroanatomy; the autonomic nervous system in particular,
人間の神経解剖学、特に自律神経系
and the so-called subtle system as described in the traditional literature on yoga.
そして、ヨガに関する伝統的な文献に記載されている いわゆる精妙なシステムです
Ultimately, the series tries to bring its viewers along this exploratory journey
最終的に、このシリーズは視聴者の皆さんを この探検の旅にご案内します
to experience these relationships through meditation as taught by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
シュリ・マタジ・ニルマラ・デヴィが教える 瞑想を通してこれらの関係を体験します
Thanks to all our viewers for joining us in this series.
このシリーズにご参加いただいた視聴者の皆様に 感謝いたします
We are on this exploration into the fascinating intersection
私たちは今 神経科学とスピリチュアリティの
of neuroscience and spirituality with Dr. Ashish Pradhan,
魅力的な交差点を探求しています 本日は神経学と心臓血管医学の
who is a distinguished leader in neurology and cardiovascular medicine. Welcome, Dr. Ashish.
卓越したリーダーであるアシシュ・プラダン博士を お迎えしています。ようこそ、アシシュ博士
Thank you, Monikaji.
ありがとう、モニカジ
Great to be back again.
また戻って来られて嬉しいです
Definitely.
本当に
My pleasure.
光栄です。
The question that I always ask you
毎回お尋ねしている 質問なのですが
about every energy center that we talk about,
今回取り上げる エネルギーセンターについても
I know today we are focused on the fifth energy center.
今日は第5のエネルギーセンターに 焦点を当てていると承知しています
So, what is the relationship between
では、このエネルギーセンターと
the autonomic nervous system and the fifth energy center?
自律神経系との関係は どのようなものでしょうか？
And then what organs does this center relate to in human anatomy?
そしてこのセンターは 人体のどの器官と関係しているのでしょうか？
We also hear about the thyroid gland, maybe a little bit about that.
甲状腺についても よく聞きますが、それについても少し教えてください
Let us begin as always.
では、いつものように始めましょう
The fifth energy center, also called the Vishuddhi Chakra,
第5のエネルギーセンター すなわちヴィシュッディ・チャクラは
has a critical role to play in human evolution.
人類の進化において 非常に重要な役割を果たしています
Each of these centers do, we have been saying from the very beginning, the whole system is integrated.
これは他のセンターにも言えることで 私たちは一貫してお話ししていますが
It is not unitary.
このシステム全体は 統合されたものであり
But this energy center is kind of special in its own way.
単独で機能するものではありません
It has 16 aspects to it according to the Sahaj teachings.
ですが、このエネルギーセンターには それ自体に固有の特別な役割があります
So if we look at human evolution from the time again,
サハジャの教えによれば このセンターには16の側面があります
from when it started, unicellular life forms
人間の進化の流れを見てみると
right up to the vertebrate animals or mammals such as us,
単細胞生物から始まり 脊椎動物、哺乳類、そして私たち人類へと続いていますが
this energy center is believed to have played two roles.
このエネルギーセンターは 2つの重要な役割を果たしてきたと考えられています
One is that this energy center controls the voice box or the larynx.
まず1つ目は、このセンターが 声帯、すなわち喉頭を司っているという点です
It also controls the movement of our arms and so on and so forth.
また、腕の動きなども このセンターによってコントロールされています
But it is a speech that I would like to focus on a little bit.
ですが、今回は「言葉を発すること」に 焦点を当ててみたいと思います
So, as we’ve said several times in this series,
これまで何度もお話ししてきたように
we have the autonomic nervous system within us—
私たちの中には自律神経系があり
which is what this series is about.
このシリーズが まさにそれをテーマにしています
Two components: sympathetic, parasympathetic.
自律神経系には 2つの構成要素があります
And the larynx or the voice box is controlled by two nerves
交感神経系と副交感神経系です
called the recurrent laryngeal nerves and they are offshoots.
喉頭、すなわち声帯は 2つの神経によって制御されています
They come from the vagus nerve and the vagus nerve comes from the midbrain.
それは反回神経と呼ばれ 迷走神経から分かれています
So the long and short of it is this, that in evolution,
そして迷走神経は 中脳から出ています
one of the reasons according to evolutionary biologists,
つまり進化の観点から言うと
one reason the Homo sapiens enjoys a pre-eminent position
進化生物学者たちによれば ホモ・サピエンスが地球上で
on this planet is its ability to communicate.
卓越した立場にある理由の ひとつは「コミュニケーション能力」にあるとされています
So communication is one of the key functions
つまり、コミュニケーションこそが
enabled by this energy center.
このエネルギーセンターによって 可能になった重要な機能のひとつです
And if you think about it, it is the power of speech.
そして考えてみると、それは 「言葉を話す力」です
Now, it is not that sounds that are produced by an organism
もちろん、生物が音を発するということは
are unique to the Homo sapiens.
ホモ・サピエンスに 特有なわけではありません
There are multiple other species,
何千、何万という 他の種も音を発します
thousands and thousands of them that produce sound.
鳥も音を出しますし 動物もそうです
Birds produce sounds, animals produce sounds, mammals such as whales and dolphins in the water,
クジラやイルカのような哺乳類も 水中で音を発します
they produce sounds.
つまり、音を出すこと自体は
So producing sound by itself is not the issue.
決して特別なことではありません
In all these organisms, this energy center probably played a role.
これらすべての生物においてもこのエネルギーセンターは 何らかの役割を果たしていた可能性があります
But in the human being, it is the most evolved
しかし、人間においては 最も進化した形で存在しており
because it allows us to form what we call speech patterns
それによって「言語パターン」 というものを形成され
that we call words and therefore language.
「言葉」、そして「言語」になったのです
And it is this language that has allowed, or the ability to create languages,
そしてこの言語や言語を作る能力
to speak languages, to communicate with each other in languages,
言語を話すこと、互いに コミュニケーションをとることが
which unfortunately sometimes also leads to divisions
私たち人類に他の種に対する 優位性を与えたのです
amongst individuals and communities and nations.
とはいえ残念ながらコミュニティ、国家間の 分断の原因にもなります
But it is this power of language that has enabled us
それでも、この「言語」という力が 他の種に対して
to gain dominance over other species.
優位に立つことを可能に してきたのです
Now, how did that pan out?
それでは、それが実際にどのように展開され
How did it provide us with an evolutionary advantage?
どのように進化上の優位性を もたらしたのかを見ていきましょう
So it is hypothesized and there is maybe a full rational background
これは仮説ですが 合理的な背景が存在します
as to how this was probably possible,
それがどのようにして可能になったのかというと
as if we go back to literally millions of years
何百万年も前にさかのぼり
and maybe hundreds of thousands of years after that,
さらにその後の数十万年
when humans started living in caves
人類が原始的な道具を使い
with primitive tools,
洞窟で生活していた時代に
they were subject to attacks by wild animals.
彼らは野生動物からの 攻撃にさらされていました
So let us say two individuals living in the same cave
例えば、同じ洞窟やその近くに 住んでいた2人の人間が
or near each other could warn each other
「近くにサーベルタイガーがいるかもしれない」と
through a pattern of speech that there may be a sabre-toothed tiger close by
言葉で警告し合えたとしたら
and then banding together, either running away from it
一緒に逃げたり
or making sure they did not get close to it.
近づかないようにしたりすることで
That allowed for a survival advantage.
生存の可能性が高まったわけです
And then we can expand on this for the next,
こうして、言語による 危険の伝達が
as much as we want, but we can see how that ability
集団の生存に 優位性をもたらしたのです
to communicate danger, forewarning of a threat
このようにして、言語能力が 脅威や危険を他者に伝える手段となり
to an individual or to a family or to a group of individuals,
個人、家族、グループ
to a settlement allowed this to happen.
あるいは 集落全体の生存を助けたのです
So in human evolution, this center has played a very important role.
つまり、人間の進化においてこのセンターは 非常に重要な役割を果たしてきたということです
The other role that the founder of this system of meditation,
この瞑想システムの創始者である シュリ・マタジ・ニルマラ・デヴィが
Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi always says,
常に語っていたもう一つの役割があります
is that it was this center that allowed us to raise our heads.
それは、このセンターが 「人間が頭を持ち上げること」を可能にしたという点です
So this cervical curvature, if you see the human skeleton
人間の骨格
or the human vertebral column in profile,
つまり背骨を横から見ると
you have the cervical curvature, then
頸椎の湾曲とその後に胸椎、腰椎
the thoracic curvature and the lumbar
そして仙骨の湾曲が続きます
and the sacral curvatures.
このような構造になっています
So when in the Neanderthal stage or in the Denisovan stage,
ネアンデルタール人や デニソワ人など
the other species that preceded the Homo sapiens, if you see the classic biology textbook
ホモ・サピエンスに先立つ 他の種を見てみると
showing the evolution of people,
進化の図でよく見るように
somebody hunched over and then gradually stood upright.
前かがみの姿勢から 徐々に直立していく様子が描かれています
This upright posture and particularly the raising of the neck
この「直立姿勢」 特に「首を持ち上げること」は
is believed to have been influenced by this energy center
このエネルギーセンターの 影響によると考えられているのです
through its control of the vertebral column as well as the nerves,
それは背骨、そして
both the sympathetic, the parasympathetic
交感神経、副交感神経
as well as the skeletal nerves that allow for the musculature
さらに骨格筋に作用する神経によって筋肉の動きを
to function in this fashion.
このように制御するためです
Besides the vocal cords, this energy center is responsible for the control of our teeth,
声帯以外にも、このエネルギーセンターは歯
our musculature here, our face, the muscles as well as our ears.
顔の筋肉、耳の機能をも司っていますですから
So again, think about it.
改めて考えてみてください
The sense of olfaction, that is a sense of smell.
嗅覚、つまり「においを感じる能力」
So the sense of smell, the ability to hear and the ability to speak are all functions
聴覚、そして言葉を話す能力
that are governed by this single energy center.
これらはすべてこの一つのエネルギーセンターに よって司られているのです
And if we go back into our evolutionary process,
そして進化の過程をさかのぼっていくと
it is believed that the sense of smell was the first
この嗅覚こそが
amongst all other senses that was evolved or that was developed
他のすべての感覚の中で 最初に進化したものだと考えられています
because in the water the little fish had to detect the presence of a predator by smelling
水中にいた小さな魚たちは、捕食者の存在を 「におい」によって察知する必要がありました
through the very primitive olfactory cells that it had,
彼らは非常に原始的な嗅覚細胞を通じて
the presence of a larger animal or a larger being
より大きな生物が発する
because of the chemicals that it emitted through its presence.
化学物質を感知していたのです
So the sense of olfaction also gave us that evolutionary advantage as it evolved.
つまり、嗅覚の進化もまた 生存上の優位性をもたらしたのです
The sense of hearing, same thing.
聴覚についても同様です
When we heard sounds, the sense of sound, I think we discussed this in a previous episode,
私たちが音を聞くという感覚 これは以前の回でも触れましたが
developed even before the cells that eventually over millions of years became our eyes
この聴覚は、目や視覚が形成されるよりも
or the sense of vision.
何百万年も前に発達していたのです
So the sense of smell and the sense of hearing allowed us that evolutionary advantage
つまり、嗅覚と聴覚は
as the human condition evolved but
人類の進化において非常に重要であり
even starting from literally billions of years ago.
その進化は、今から何十億年も前に 始まったものなのです
So this energy center allowed us to evolve,
このように、このエネルギーセンターは 私たちを進化させ
to gain what we might dare use the word consciousness.
そして「意識」と呼ばれるものを 獲得することを可能にしたのです
Who we are as individuals, as a collective,
「私たちは何者か」という意識、個人として 集団として存在する「私たち」という意識は
as a body started from this particular energy center.
このエネルギーセンターから 始まったとされています
And that is why this center from a Sahaj point of view
そのため、サハジャの観点から見ると
is responsible for allowing us to have a sense of collectivity
このセンターは「集合性の感覚」を もたらす役割を担っているのです
which we will deal with later in this episode.
そしてこのテーマについては このエピソードの後半でさらに深く触れていきます
it sits here in front of the trachea in this upper part
甲状腺は、この喉の前方 気管の前に位置しています
and the thyroid gland secretes hormones
そして甲状腺は 私たちにもおなじみのホルモン
that we are all familiar with, that is thyroxine
すなわちサイロキシン（T4）と
and triiodothyronine, the thyroid T3, T4. Most of us who have undergone exams, know
トリヨードサイロニン（T3）を分泌します 健康診断などで
that your internist will ask for the levels of those hormones.
これらのホルモンの数値を確認するよう医師から 指示されたことがある方も多いでしょう
Those hormones are very important because they are related
これらのホルモンは非常に重要であり
to neural development, the development of the brain.
神経の発達、つまり脳の発達に関係しています
So the thyroid hormones help in what is called
甲状腺ホルモンは
neurogenesis which means the growth of cells.
神経新生（ニューロジェネシス）
They are important for synaptogenesis which means
つまり神経同士の接続
the connectivity between these neurons is very important,
この形成にも重要です
we will deal with this in the final episode.
これについては 最終回でも触れる予定です
But these are synapses through which neurons talk to each other.
シナプスとは、神経細胞同士が コミュニケーションを取る部分のことです
The presence of these hormones is very important for optimal development of the brain
そしてこのホルモンが存在することで 脳の最適な発達が可能になります
and unfortunately we know that individuals who from birth
残念ながら私たちは知っています このホルモンが生まれつき欠乏している人は
or lack this hormone do suffer from neurological conditions
神経学的な障害や
and even sometimes mental retardation.
ときには知的障害を抱える可能性があるのです
So these hormones are important and that is why
ですので、これらのホルモンは非常に重要であり
this energy center, which is the fifth energy center,
だからこそ、この第5のエネルギーセンターは
is so critical for human evolution, for the development of the human brain,
人類の進化において決定的に重要なのです それは人間の脳の発達
the overall development of the nervous system, and the sense of collectivity that we feel
そして神経系全体の発達、私たちが感じる 「集合性の感覚」にもつながっているのです
both as an individual as part of a larger organism.
個としてとより大きな存在の一部としての自分この全てに 関わっているのがこのエネルギーセンターなのです
I know this answer is very long
長くなってしまいましたが
but there's one interesting hypothesis
ここで最近提唱された
that has recently been postulated is that this energy center
興味深い仮説を紹介したいと思います
probably also controlled
それは、このエネルギーセンターが
the development of the entire skeleton, not just the musculature.
筋肉だけでなく、骨格全体の発達にも 関与していたのではないかというものです
But also the bones-muscles essentially sit on the bones,
つまり筋肉は骨の上に存在するわけですが
the bones provide the framework, the muscles sit on that.
骨が骨格の土台を提供し その上に筋肉が乗るという構造です
If you have seen images or in museums or sketches
博物館などでご覧になったことがあるか あるいはスケッチやイメージなどで
or what we know from skeletons that have been discovered
見たことがあるかもしれませんが 私たちの遠い祖先の骨格を見ると
of our ancestors from the distant past, the lower jaw protrudes forward.
下顎が前方に突き出しているのが わかるかと思います
So the front part of the face, the upper part of the face
つまり顔の前部、上部は後方にあり
sits at the back, the lower jaw juts forward.
下顎が突き出ているという構造です
You see that in apes, in great apes.
これは類人猿に見られる特徴でもあります
Whereas with the human being, the jaw has gone back
一方、人間では この顎が後退し
and it is much more level and the reason for that is hypothesized
より水平に近い構造に変化しています そしてその理由として考えられているのが
to be that this muscle that controls our mastication, the chewing
咀嚼を司る筋肉――つまり
with the lower jaw that goes up and down when we chew food
下顎を上下に動かすこの筋肉に関係する
which is the lower bone which is called as the mandible bone.
「下顎骨（mandible bone）」の 遺伝的な変化です
The mandible bone was much more stronger and protruded forward but through a gene
この下顎骨はかつては、もっと強く、前に 突き出していましたが、ある遺伝子の働きによって
that controlled for its development is thought
その構造が変化したと考えられています
to have changed the structure of the bone
つまり、その遺伝子が
to the extent that it allowed for the mandible to go back
下顎骨を後方に移動させるように働いたことで
and because of that the biomechanical forces were reduced
顎にかかる生体力学的な負荷が減少し
or there was less stress on it and that allowed
その結果として
for the skull to grow.
頭蓋骨の拡大が可能になったのです
Now let's put it all together.
では、それらをすべて つなぎ合わせてみましょう
The lower part of the face which is the mandible, if it was longer it caused more stress here
顔の下部である下顎骨が もし長すぎると、ここにより大きな負担がかかります
and therefore it pulled this down and did not allow
そのため、これが下に引っ張られ 頭蓋骨のこの2つの部分が拡がるのを妨げます
these two parts of the cranium, the skull to expand
つまり、頭蓋骨のこの2つの部分が拡がることができず
and therefore what was inside it, the brain.
その中にあるもの つまり脳にも影響が及ぶのです
The brain couldn't expand but because this went back,
脳は拡がることができませんでしたが これが後方に移動したことで
biomechanical forces reduced here,
この部分の生体力学的な力が減少し、その結果 頭蓋骨のこの部分への圧力が
on both sides,
両側で軽減されました
to allow for that space for this mass of cells inside called the brain to expand.
その結果として、内部にある脳という この細胞の塊が拡がるための空間が確保されたのです
So it is absolutely fascinating to see, and of course hypothesize, we cannot prove this,
これを見ることができるのは本当に興味深いことですし もちろん仮説であって、証明はできません
there is no way to easily prove this, but it is a fact
これを簡単に証明する方法はありませんが、 1つの事実として言えるのは
that had the mandible been not controlled
もし下顎骨がコントロールされていなかったり
or had it not gone back, maybe the ability
後方に引っ込んでいなかったとしたら
of the cranium to grow and therefore for the brain to expand
頭蓋骨の成長能力や それによって脳が拡がる能力が
which makes this possible, you and I to speak, would perhaps not have been possible.
つまり、あなたや私がこうして話すことができる この仕組み自体が、おそらく不可能だったかもしれません
So this energy center is absolutely critical, it's fascinating, it's extremely complex
ですから、このエネルギーセンターは本当に重要であり とても興味深く、そして非常に複雑ですが
but it has probably played a stellar role in human evolution.
しかし、それはおそらく人類の進化において 卓越した（または極めて重要な）役割を果たしてきたのでしょう
Definitely.
間違いありませんね
It's such a sophisticated mechanism in this evolution.
この進化の過程において 非常に洗練されたメカニズムです
It's so interesting to learn about this.
これについて学ぶのはとても面白いですね
So Dr. Ashish, as we understand that every center
アシシュ先生、私たちは、あらゆるチャクラに
has some qualities that an individual manifests
個人が現すべき特質があると理解していますが
and then is there any potential scientific basis
サハジャ・ヨガの教えにある
to the Sahaj teaching that collective consciousness
「集合意識はこのセンターから始まる」 という考え方に対して
begins from this center?
何か科学的な根拠はあるのでしょうか？
Yes, it's a little complex mechanism or a complex explanation
はい、これは少し複雑な仕組み または複雑な説明なのですが
but we'll try to simplify this.
なるべく分かりやすくしてみますね
So along with the control of the vocal box, of the larynx,
声帯箱、すなわち喉頭の制御
of the vocal cords within the larynx
喉頭内の声帯の制御
and the other parts within the face,
そして顔の中の他の部分の制御に加えて
this energy center is also believed to control two other plexuses.
このエネルギーセンターは さらに2つの神経叢も司ると考えられています
One is the cervical plexus and the other one is the brachial plexus
1つは頸神経叢、もう1つは腕神経叢です
and these are again as we have discussed, plexuses are
これらはいずれも、以前に説明したとおり
groups of nerves, they contain both sympathetic,
神経の集まりであり 交感神経、副交感神経
parasympathetic and sensory components.
そして感覚神経の要素を すべて含んでいます
Now the brachial plexus controls the movement of our arms.
さて、腕神経叢は私たちの腕の動きを制御しています
It makes the movement of our arms possible that helps us to communicate.
それによって腕の動きが可能となり 私たちがコミュニケーションをとる助けとなっているのです
The interesting fact is that so far as microdissection
興味深い事実として、顕微解剖技術によって 私たちが調べられる範囲では
techniques have allowed us to examine,
私たちの指先には副交感神経の末端は存在しません
we do not have parasympathetic nerve endings in the tips of our fingers.
存在するのは、交感神経の末端のみです
We only have sympathetic nerve endings
私たちは、副交感神経が
and although we believe that parasympathetic controls
内臓のすべてを制御していると信じています
everything within the viscera, we have discussed this before
以前に説明しましたが
through the vagus nerve for the most part
これは主に迷走神経を通じて行われているのです
but there are no sympathetic nerve endings in the tips of our fingers.
ですが、指先には副交感神経の末端はありません
Now how is that important?
では、それがなぜ重要なのでしょうか？
It's important from a Sahaj point of view because when
これはサハジャの観点から重要なのです。なぜなら
the inner energy rises and it crosses this energy center,
内なるエネルギーが上昇し、このエネルギーセンター
the fifth energy center within the central channel,
すなわち中央のチャンネルにある第5のエネルギーセンターを 通過するとき
through mechanisms that are physiologically very difficult
そのメカニズムは生理学的に非常に理解が難しく まだ現代の人間の科学では十分に解明されていません
to appreciate, not yet, I mean human science
つまり、現在の人間の科学は
has not reached that stage but probably one day will,
そこまでの段階には達していませんが おそらくいつかは到達するでしょう
however it allows us to feel reality
しかしながら、それ（エネルギーの上昇）は 私たちに「現実」を感じさせてくれます
beyond the cognitive perception.
つまり、認知的な知覚を超えた現実を 感じることができるのです
And that is we can feel what are called as vibrations,
つまり私たちは 「ヴァイブレーション（波動）」と呼ばれるもの
this cool breeze that does blow through the tips of our fingers.
指先を通して吹いてくるこの涼しい風を 感じることができるのです
Now let's put it all together.
では、これらすべてをまとめてみましょう
The energy rises through the central channel which is parasympathetic.
エネルギーは、副交感神経である中央のチャンネルを 通って上昇していきます
It is not sympathetic, it is parasympathetic.
それは交感神経ではなく 副交感神経なのです
However the ability to feel the rising of this energy
しかし、このエネルギーの上昇や
and the consequence of that rising
その上昇による影響を感じる能力は
is felt through the tips of our fingers
交感神経である指先を通じて
which is sympathetic.
感じ取られるのです
And therefore it is at the level of this energy center
ですから、このエネルギーセンターのレベルで
because of these two plexuses, the brachial plexus
これら2つの神経叢、つまり腕神経叢と
and the cervical plexus but predominantly the brachial plexus
頸神経叢、特に腕神経叢が関係しています
which innervates our hands and the nerves in our hands,
腕神経叢は私たちの手や 手の中の神経を支配しているため
we can clearly see how this energy center
このエネルギーセンターが
allows us to feel these vibrations.
私たちにヴァイブレーションを感じさせてくれるということが 非常に明確に見えてきます
Because of Sahaj,
サハジャによって
when this energy rises and you can feel it,
このエネルギーが上昇し、それを感じることができたとき
this ability to feel allows you to get this realization
その「感じる能力」によって 私たちはある気づきを得るのです
that you are not just you but you are part of a larger reality.
それは、自分は単なる「自分」ではなく より大きな現実の一部であるという気づきです
That you exist as part of a larger system, of a larger reality that transcends you.
つまり、自分は自分を超えた もっと大きな現実の一部として存在しているのです
And this is the beginning of what is called collective consciousness.
そして、これが「集合意識（コレクティブ・コンシャスネス）」 と呼ばれるものの始まりなのです
So we have individual consciousness: I am breathing,
私たちには「個人の意識」があります たとえば私は呼吸している
I am seeing you, I am hearing you, you are seeing me,
私はあなたを見ている、私はあなたの声を聞いている あなたも私を見ている
so that is our individual consciousness.
それが私たちの「個の意識」なのです
But when this inner energy rises, it is only through
しかし、この内なるエネルギーが上昇するとき
the awakening of this energy center
それはこのエネルギーセンターが 目覚めることによってのみ
that allows us to feel through the sympathetic system
副交感神経系で実際に 何が起きているかを
what is actually happening within the parasympathetic system.
交感神経系を通して 「感じる」ことができるようになるのです
So let me repeat that.
もう一度繰り返します
These nerves at the tips of our fingers do not have parasympathetic endings.
私たちの指先にある神経の末端には 副交感神経は届いていません
So what is otherwise happening within the parasympathetic,
つまり本来であれば 副交感神経系の中で
we would have no ability to know.
何が起きているのかを 私たちは知ることができないのです
It is only because of this energy center that we can feel
しかし、このエネルギーセンターのおかげで
this sensation in our hands - what is happening
私たちは手のひらで この感覚――つまり
within the parasympathetic nervous system.
副交感神経系で起こっている現象を
And which is why the founder of this system of meditation,
交感神経系を通して 「感じる」ことができるのです
Shri Mataji, always used to say that in order to feel
ですから、この瞑想システムの創始者である シュリ・マタジがいつも言っていたのは
This cool breeze, what She called vibrations,
この涼しい風、彼女はそれを 「ヴァイブレーション」と呼んでいました
you need to have this energy center that is in a very good condition,
それを感じるためには この第5のエネルギーセンターが
that is in a healthy condition and therefore it is very important
健康で良好な状態に ある必要があるということです
to keep this center in a great working condition
だからこそ、このセンターを 健やかに保つことがとても重要なのです
so that you can feel it.
そうすれば、あなたはそれを感じることができます
It is a bit complex, but that is how we begin to comprehend
少し複雑ではありますが このようにして私たちは
and to experience collective consciousness.
「集合意識」というものを 理解し、体験し始めるのです
Well, Dr. Ashish, every single discussion with you has been so much interesting.
アシシュ博士、本当に 毎回のお話がとても興味深いです
We have learnt a lot with you and I do want to once again
今回も多くの学びがありましたし
thank you for your time today
改めて時間をとっていただき 本当にありがとうございました
and we look forward to talking to you on the next episode
次回は、次のエネルギーセンターについて
about the next energy center.
お話できるのを楽しみにしています
Thanks once again.
今回もありがとうございました
Thank you again.
ありがとうございました
And we would encourage our viewers to follow the meditation video that is going to be guided
そして視聴者の皆様には、これから流れる 瞑想ビデオをぜひご覧いただきたいと思います
by the founder of this meditation and we wish you all the very best in your experiment
この瞑想は創始者ご自身のガイドによるものです 皆様の実験と体験が素晴らしいものとなりますように
and this experience with Sahaj meditation.
サハジャ瞑想によるこの旅路が 良きものとなりますように
Thank you.
ありがとうございました
Shri Mataji: Now we come to the other center of Vishuddhi chakra.
シュリ・マタジ：さて、ヴィシュッディ・チャクラの もう一つの側面に移りましょう
This is the most important in the sense
このチャクラは非常に重要です
that it ends all your evolution as far as human life is concerned.
なぜなら、人間としての進化のすべてが このチャクラで完結するからです
This has got sixteen petals.
このチャクラには16枚の花弁があります
Outside in the gross it manifests the cervical plexus
粗大なレベル（物理的な次元）では このチャクラは頸神経叢として現れます
and controls your ear, nose, throat, muscles,
そして、耳、鼻、喉、筋肉
your eyes and your face.
目、そして顔全体を 制御しています
Also it controls the first bone and all the bones that go up to the cranial bones.
また、このチャクラは最初の骨（首の骨）から 頭蓋骨に至るすべての骨をも司っています
It is the center of your responsibility by which you feel responsibility.
このチャクラは「責任感」の中枢であり、私たちが「責任」を 感じることができるのはこのチャクラのおかげです
But when this center is awakened, the greater center represents them here,
しかし、このチャクラが目覚めるとき より高次のセンターがここに現れます
because all these centers are represented again in a bigger way in the brain.
なぜなら、すべてのチャクラは脳の中に より大きく拡張された形で再び現れるからです
So this center when it is awakened, which is a bigger, larger center of this,
ですので、このチャクラが目覚めると そのより大きなセンターが働き始め
you become collectively conscious.
あなたは「集合意識」を持つようになります
This is the center of collectivity.
このヴィシュッディ・チャクラは 「集合性」のチャクラなのです
Keep your eyes closed.
目を閉じてください
First of all, please put your right hand on your heart.
まずは右手を胸に当ててください
All the time the left hand is towards Me.
常に左手は私の方に向けてください
Now, here you have to say in your heart, with all sincerity, Mother, am I the Spirit?
こで、心の中で誠実に 「母よ、私はスピリットですか？」と
Ask the question three times in your heart.
心の中で3回質問してください
This is a very fundamental question.
これは非常に基本的な質問です
Now bring the right hand on to the left hand side of your stomach,
次に、右手をお腹の左側
in the upper part.
上部に当ててください
Here press it.
ここを押してください
Now this is the center of your mastery, your guidance, your guru Tattva, as they say.
これが、いわゆるあなたのマスタリー（熟達） ガイダンス（指導）グル・タットヴァのセンターです
So ask a question, Mother, am I my own master?
それで、質問してください、母さん 私は自分自身の指導者ですか?
This is the question to be asked three times.
この質問を3回行ってください
Mother, am I my own master?
お母さん、私は自分自身の指導者ですか？
Now bring your right hand down below in the lower part of the abdomen.
次に、右手をお腹の下部 左側に移動させてください
Now this is the center from which all the Divine work is done,
ここはすべての神聖な仕事が行われるセンターです
all the pure work is done.
すべての純粋な仕事がここで行われます
So to ask six times, because this center has got six petals,
このセンターには6枚の花弁があるため
Mother, please give me pure knowledge.
「母よ、私に純粋な知識を与えてください」
Six times you just ask.
と6回お願いしてください
As a result of this asking the Kundalini starts getting awakened.
この祈りにより、クンダリーニが目覚め始めます
Now to help the Kundalini to rise you have to cooperate with Her.
クンダリーニの上昇を助けるには 協力しなければなりません
So please put your right hand on the left hand side
右手をお腹の左側、上部に移動させてください
in the upper part of your abdomen and press it on the stomach.
お腹の上部を押してください
Now here you have to say with full confidence,
ここで、自信を持って「母よ、私は 自分自身のマスターです」と10回言ってください
to help the Kundalini to rise, Mother, I am my own master.
これは10の戒律であり、「母よ、私は 自分自身のマスターです」と言ってください
This you have to say ten times.
これを10回言います
These are the ten commandments which you have to say,
これらはあなたが 言わなければならない十戒です
that Mother, I am my own master.
母よ、私は自分自身の指導者です
Now, ten times with full confidence.
さあ、自信を持って10回
Now please raise your right hand to your heart.
では、右手を胸に当ててください
Now here you have to say, again with full confidence,
ここでもう一度、自信を持ってこう言いましょう
Mother, I am the Spirit.
「母よ、私はスピリットです」
This is the truth, you are the Spirit.
これは真実です あなたはスピリット（聖霊）なのです
But you have to say with full confidence, Mother, I am the Spirit.
完全な自信を持ってこう言いましょう 「母よ、私はスピリットです」
This you have to say twelve times.
これを12回言いましょう
Now one has to know that God Almighty is the ocean of love.
全能の神は「愛の海」であるということを 知らなければなりません
But above all He is the ocean of forgiveness.
神は赦しの大海なのです
So He forgives.
だから神は許します
Whatever wrong you do He forgives.
あなたがどんな悪いことをしても 神は許してくれます
So don't feel guilty and put your right hand across
だから罪悪感を感じずに右手を
on the left hand side in the corner which is made by your neck and your shoulder.
左側の首と肩の付け根に当てましょう
Now here you have to say again with full confidence,
ここでもう一度自信を持って言いましょう
sixteen times, Mother, I am not guilty.
「母よ、私には罪悪感はありません」
Sixteen times.
16回言いましょう
I am not guilty at all.
私には罪悪感はありません
Please say it.
言ってみてください
Now raise your hand across on your forehead and it's a very important center.
次に、額に手を当ててください ここは非常に重要なセンターです
Here you have to say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
ここでは心から言ってください 「母よ、私はすべての人を許します」
Please say it from your heart.
心から言ってください
How many times is not the point.
何何回でも結構です
Mother, I forgive everyone.
「母よ、私はすべての人を許します」
Now some would say that it's very difficult to forgive.
許すのは非常に難しいと言う人もいるでしょう
But it's a myth that we do not forgive or we forgive.
しかし、私たちが許さない あるいは許すというのは幻想なのです
We do not do anything in both the cases.
どちらにしても 実際には私たちは何もしていません
But if we don't forgive then we play into wrong hands.
けれども、もし許さなければ、 私たちは誤った力の手中に落ちてしまいます
So please say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
だから、どうか心から言ってください 「母よ、私はすべての人を許します。」
Now please take your hand on the back agnya, the same center, on the back side of your head
今度は、手を後頭部のアギャチャクラ （同じセンター）に当ててください
and allow your head to rest on it and push it back a little bit.
頭を手の上に預け、少し後ろに押し下げてください
Now here you have to say for your satisfaction,
ここでは、あなた自身の満足のために言ってください
because you always feel guilty, that, O Divine, if I have done anything wrong,
なぜなら、あなたはいつも罪悪感を抱えているからです 「おお、神よ、もし私が何か間違いを犯していたなら
please forgive me.
どうか私をお許しください
Please forgive me, from your heart.
どうか心から「私をお許しください」と言ってください
Stretch your hand fully and put your center of your palm
次に、手を大きく広げて、手のひらの中心を
on top of the fontanel bone area, which was a very soft bone in your childhood.
頭頂部の泉門（フォントネル）に当ててください それは子どもの頃に柔らかかった場所です
Press it hard.
強く押してください
Press hard your scalp.
頭皮をしっかり押します
Now you have to move it seven times saying one thing, which you have to ask for,
そして、ここで7回、円を描くように強く動かしながら 次のようにお願いしてください
Mother, please give us My Self-realization, because I cannot force on you.
「母よ、どうか私にセルフリアリゼーションをお与えください」 私はそれをあなたに強制することはできません
So you have to ask for it.
ですから、あなたがそれを求めなければなりません
Seven times press it hard and move it seven times very hard.
7回、強く押しながら、頭頂でしっかり回してください
Slowly saying that.
ゆっくりと、「母よ、どうか私にセルフリアリゼーションを お与えください」と言いながら